You can get work done a number of different ways on Z.
你可以用多種方式在 IBM Z 上完成工作。
Some people prefer a fully graphical experience, like what you get through Zoe.
有些人偏好完全圖形化的體驗，就像透過 Zoe 一樣。
Other people like to keep it simple, but still want a little graphical context,
其他人喜歡保持簡單，但仍想要一些圖形化的上下文，
like what you get through the panels of ISPF.
就像使用 ISPF 的面板一樣。
Then there's some people who really just don't want anything between them and the system,
還有人不想在他們和系統之間加任何介面，
and they prefer to issue commands straight through TSO.
他們偏好直接透過 TSO 發出指令。
In ZOS, TSO stands for Time Sharing Option,
在 z/OS 中，TSO 代表 Time Sharing Option，
and it's basically the environment that lets the OS be made available to multiple users at the same time.
它基本上是讓作業系統能同時提供給多個使用者的環境。
There are a ton of commands in TSO, and this lesson, we're going to take a look at just a few of them.
TSO 有許多指令，這一課我們將只看其中幾個。
There are three primary ways of entering TSO commands.
輸入 TSO 指令主要有三種方式。
One, through the ISPF primary menu, going to option number 6.
一、透過 ISPF 主要選單，選擇第 6 項。
Two, on the command option line of an ISPF panel,
二、在 ISPF 面板的命令選項列上，
on that line, anything that starts with TSO will be interpreted as a TSO command.
該列上任何以 TSO 開頭的，都會被視為 TSO 命令。
And three, on the TSO ready prompt screen.
三、在 TSO 準備好提示畫面上。
When you do it this way, it's known as native mode.
用這種方式執行時，稱為原生模式。
A command is made up of a command name, followed by one or more operands.
命令由命令名稱組成，後接一個或多個運算元。
Think of it like the command is the thing that you want done,
可以想成命令是你要做的事，
and the operands are the details of how you'd like it to be done.
而運算元是你希望怎麼執行的細節。
For example, if I were to tell you move something, you would need more information,
舉例來說，如果我告訴你移動某物，你需要更多資訊，
like what am I moving, where am I moving it to,
例如我要移動什麼，要移到哪裡，
am I moving it with a forklift, a train, a truck, or am I just carrying it with my hands.
我是用堆高機、火車、卡車搬運，還是徒手搬？
The how goes in the operands.
操作數中包含動作細節。
Commands and operands are not case sensitive, meaning they can be typed out in lowercase or uppercase.
指令與操作數不區分大小寫，可用大寫或小寫輸入。
We'll often type them out in uppercase though, just so they stand out more as commands and not random text.
不過我們常用大寫，讓指令更突出，不會被誤認為一般文字。
There are two types of operands, positional and keywords.
操作數分為位置型和關鍵字型兩種。
A positional operand needs to come after the command and in a certain order.
位置型操作數需跟在指令後，並按特定順序排列。
The documentation for commands will tell you exactly what order they need to be in and which ones are required.
指令文件會詳細說明正確順序及必填項目。
And we'll get into how you get that information shortly.
我們接著會說明如何取得這些資訊。
There's also keyword operands.
還有關鍵字操作數。
This is usually used to turn on a feature or set a certain mode.
通常用來啟動功能或設定特定模式。
So in this example, the command is list ds.
在此範例中，指令是 list ds。
That's what we want it to do.
這正是我們想要它做的事。
We learned earlier that list ds stands for list dataset,
我們之前學過 list ds 代表 list dataset，
and we can use it to show us a whole bunch of information about a dataset.
我們可以用它來顯示關於資料集的大量資訊。
The positional operand is something that comes right after the command name, and that's the dataset we're listing.
位置參數是緊接在指令名稱後面的內容，那是我們要列出的資料集。
One additional thing to note here, if what you want to put in the operand is a list of multiple items,
另外要注意的是，如果你想在參數中放多個項目列表，
you just put that list in parentheses.
只要將該列表放在括號內即可。
And then lastly is the keyword operand.
最後是關鍵字參數。
That tells the command to list the members of this dataset.
它告訴指令要列出此資料集的成員。
For this lesson, we'll be referencing the zos-tsoe command reference manual attached to this lesson.
本課程將參考本課程附加的 zos-tsoe 指令參考手冊。
It's a good book. A lot better than the movie version.
這是本好書，比電影版本好多了。
You can use the help command to obtain information about the function, syntax, and operands of the commands and subcommands,
你可以使用 help 指令取得指令和子指令的功能、語法和運算子資訊，
as well as information about certain messages.
以及某些訊息的相關資訊。
So you can type help list ds operands, and you'll get a listing of all the operands for the list ds command.
所以你可以輸入 help list ds operands，就會取得 list ds 指令所有運算子的清單。
You can also type help list ds all, and you'll get all the information about the list ds command.
你也可以輸入 help list ds all，就會取得 list ds 指令的全部資訊。
In the next lesson, we'll take a look at the allocate and delete commands.
下一課我們將介紹 allocate 和 delete 指令。